there's a little there's a question
regarding kalamazoo
so
the famous sutra that's often being
quoted where buddha
encourages people of kalama
people of kalama
that came to talk to him to uh to learn
how to think basically for oneself
so this
various things to be avoided when it comes to
things to be avoided when it comes to
one's own reasoning things that would be
contradictory or would constitute what's known as the
or would constitute what's known as the
logical fallacies
so
obviously i'm not going to read the
whole city here it can be included in
the description but the point is columns
were in doubt because there were many
different teachings many different
teachers propagating many different
teachings uh coming coming around and
then they they
they couldn't
they were wondering how can they know
for uh for themselves which one of those
teachers is right and which one isn't
so um
the buddha then tells them that it is
quite proper that they're doubtful
because when you're hearing
contradictory instructions uh you can't
say they're all right
um so you have to then start
well you have to then find some sort of
criteria that can help you discern which
ones right which ones are wrong or which one
right which ones are wrong or which one
are which ones are less likely to be
wrong which one are more likely to be to
be right and so on so the first one is
not to go
not to go upon
what has been acquired by repeated
hearing from different people by majority so
from different people by majority so
not to go simply upon tradition not to
go upon hearsay not to go upon what's in
the scriptures
scriptures
not upon surmise
not upon an axiom not upon faulty
reasoning not upon bias not upon
another's apparent uh competence
competence of another confidence of
another and not upon mere reasoning um
consideration that oh this teacher this
monk is our teacher and thus we just go
up on what he says
so the first one is not to go upon what
has been acquired by repeated hearing
um that's often used
used as an argument um
on its own so so the point of all these
things is like not to use
these criteria as sole criterias for
deciding what's right what's wrong
in other words you have to take
responsibility for choosing what criteria you want to
for choosing what criteria you want to
use
and therefore you can't say oh this is
right because the majority said so or
this is right because of our teacher
said so no this is right because i chose
to regard it as right on the basis of
what i heard from my teacher or on the
basis of what majority says
in other words majority
cannot um provide
the the basis for validity of the
argument you are the one choosing to use
majority as an excuse for the validity
of the argument
so in this case don't don't do that
don't go upon that which has been here
which has been acquired by repeated
hearing so you've been hearing the same
thing here and same thing there and same
thing somewhere else on and on and on
and on through like many different
sources but you've been hearing the same
thing and for some people that will be enough
and for some people that will be enough
uh to take that thing to be the truth
so yeah the point here that
that it's useful to add
is that sometimes when people
come across the conflicting instructions
they would choose to side with
instruction that came from the majority
simply because it's the majority of people
because it's the majority of people
saying and thus
all these people are more likely to be
right than this one person who says that
but that in itself as i said it's a it's
a plain logical fallacy because it's not
about how many people are saying
something it's about whether that thing
it's about whether that thing
has the universal truth in it the
universal truth that we're going to
discuss further on in this talk
because if such if such a
if such if such a
reasoning would have followed then
nobody would have ever listened to the
buddha the buddha was literally the only one
the buddha was literally the only one
in the entire cosmos
saying certain things
certain things
teaching the dharma nobody else can
teach the dumb except the buddha so if
people were to go by the criteria of
majority is always right dhamma would
have not arisen ever
um and uh and that's that's that's kind
of a contradictory
standpoint for somebody who wants to
practice the dharma today
yet dismisses the instructions because
they're not part of the established
majority or
or
it's you know i just heard it once and
so on no it doesn't matter if you just
hear it briefly from one person and
never ever again from anybody else it's
still required it's still it still um
deserves the equal amount of
consideration and and um and sort of
contrasting against the principle of
greed aversion delusion non-greed
non-aversion on delusion
um and then and then on the basis of
that you can decide if it's right or
wrong not on the basis of how many
people agree with it or not
even if the thing is the truth it's a
mistake to take it simply on the basis
of repeated hearing
oh the majority said so that's it who am
i to disagree well that's what will says
here you should be the one who will then
question that despite
uh vast majority saying that's that is
so
so you question it by the principles
that he outlines in the same sutta which
is uh
these things are good and these things
are bad things that are good are things
that are
lust free greed free ill will free
distraction free things basically that
are not avoiding responsibility by
taking up responsibility
things in the bad are things that are
rooted in greed aversion delusion and
everything else desires sensuality
everything else that revolves around
them so
so
majority might be saying something and
whether that's right or wrong
you can reflect uh on the basis of the
principle of greed non-greed aversion
non-aversion delusion on the soul if for
example majority says no no no
like household life is good and practice
of dharma is not so good or it's not too
necessary to become a monk and so on
you ask yourself okay so
the whole world might be agreeing upon
this but
which one of those two ways one claim is
right the other one claim is wrong
leads to dispassion or passion leads to
greed aversion delusion or freedom from
greed aversion delusion which one leads
to
liberation from from
acquisitions from ownership from burden
and which one leads to accumulation of
those so you use that now as a criteria to see
so you use that now as a criteria to see
whether the whole majority is right or
wrong not simply well everybody said so thus
not simply well everybody said so thus
it must be right
so this the similar the one that follows
is that don't go simply upon tradition
it's very similar it's just like a more
more specific type of majority the
majority of my tradition and you often
encounter that in the in the monastic
settings whereby
like you know the monks that themselves
will be quoting kalamazuta at the same
time refuse to simply put tradition in
question or the traditional ways so it's
not for the sake of dismantling
tradition or fighting against it it's
simply for the sake of not using that as
assault criteria because that's not
where greed the version delusion are so
if your goal is to practice the dharma
for the liberation of your mind
none of these external criterias can be
taken as trustworthy because greater
version delusion are on the level of
your own intention you don't mind your
own choices
and that can only be visible to you if
you have stopped resorting to these
external criterias of self-justification
oh well i don't i don't think about it
much because uh that's just how we do it
in this tradition and to make things
worse today you know having been so long
since it would have passed away
often you find buddhist traditions
that are completely the opposite of what
the buddha said you should do
and people would know that so in full
awareness of the buddha said one thing
tradition says another thing but i go
with the tradition because you know it's
been done for so long
or because the majority of the people
that i align myself with agree with this
or on a more personal level out of uh
out of fear
out of a fear to uh
just to stand out so although i know
what the buddha said
the tradition requires me to do
something else i'll just do something
else so nobody will criticize me or
blame me
but then you should really evaluate why
you want to practice them in the first
place to sue the majority or to free
yourself from samsara once and for all
all of that results in avoidance of
personal responsibility and if there is
no taking up a personal responsibility
there is no practice for dhamma
so that's why even if the tradition is
right you mustn't take it on the level
of tradition you must take it on the
level of the personal responsibility for
great diversion delusion or freedom from
those so the point of um
so the point of um
the point of not going by mere tradition
it's not you know anarchy and and um
sort of rebellion against it the point
is
that's not uh if you are going by it uh
you are avoiding responsibility so you
have to take it up so if you choose to
follow tradition you choose to because
you made a choice to do so so it's on
you so if you choose to do something the
so if you choose to do something the
tradition says you should do you do it
because you choose to do it
not because tradition said so and i'm
absolved from responsibility for doing
so so it always comes back on you and
the sooner you step a step away from
that group belonging of the tradition or
majority or we are in this together the
sooner your practice will start
so then the the third one don't go upon
hearsay so
itikira the the pali word and it's the
whole point is hearsay just uh you heard
something seems right and that's it that's enough
seems right and that's it that's enough
on its own to kind of accept that
argument and that's that's even more
careless than the the previous two two
examples also uh anecdotal evidence would come
also uh anecdotal evidence would come
under this as well rumor and so on so
it's like
oh such and such ajan said so something
happened to him thus that's the truth
that applies to all of us
or such and such person interprets
certain rules or practices in this way i
heard that from somebody else
uh but that's good enough for me to to
follow it
don't go upon what's in the scripture
and that's an interesting one so
basically the authority of the texts and
you find that same even in the early
buddhist you know
suttas not in them but in people's attitude
not in them but in people's attitude
towards them
like doesn't matter how authoritative text
doesn't matter how authoritative text
might be the point is
the entirety of it it's still on the
level of what the buddha called phrasing
so there is phrasing of something and
then there is meaning of what you just
put in phrases
and um scriptures are the phrasing which
means every single individual that chooses to
every single individual that chooses to
read the scriptures is responsible for
the meaning they infer from those
phrases and that also applies
and that also applies
even to the individual terms and
designations in the individual words
even when you're just doing a mere
translation you're already coming with
certain preconceived notions of
the meaning behind those terms
so then when you compile some broader
meaning on the basis of a broader
uh collection of phrases all of those
individual little
meanings that you have inferred do kind
of influence the general understanding
that you got from it so that's why that
taking up responsibility from um on the
smallest level it's really important
so that's why even if it's the buddha's
words written down accurately in the sutras
written down accurately in the sutras
and we all agree this is what he said
that's still not an objective truth
objective truth is the
assembly of those phrases the
arrangement that's the objectivity of it
meaning from it can never be placed
on the scripture itself
and that's what what we said in the
other talks the whole point
of of practice of studying and trying to
understand the buddhist phrases
instructions designations and so on is
to be free from greater virgin delusion
to be free from passion
so
study of phrases if it's not resulting
in freedom from greater version delusion
you are not understanding its meaning it
doesn't matter how well skilled and
informed and and and scholarly trained
and understanding every single etymology
and permutation and declinations of the
world are
if you are not at least sort of free
from greed aversion delusion practice
into that none of these phrases apply to
you because that's what the phrases send
because that's what the phrases send
themselves
if somebody were to understand the
buddha's instruction they would have at
least the right view
so this particular example don't go up
on what's in the scripture it's it's
it's quite it's quite relevant
for most of us because
you do have to start somewhere you do
have to start from some sort of faith in
some sort of authority
that can tell you how to practice
but it's
it's easy then to fall into a view that
that's the truth in itself and that you
are not responsible for how you're
already approaching it with your
attitude and preconceived notions and
implied meanings and so on so yes you
need the right phrasing but as the other
requisite for the right view is you also
need to have you also need to know
how to attend things properly and that's
pretty much what this comes down to
if you attend things properly you will
know that correct understanding of the
meaning of the phrasing has to result in
this passion if there is no dispassion
there is no disenchantment there is no
relinquishment there is no right view
you are not understanding the meaning of
the phrasing doesn't matter how
satisfied and how much clarity you might
have on account of your you know
informational collection of all the
phrases and that you have memorized and
know by heart and so on
so
don't put the responsibility for the
meaning of what you're trying to
understand on the level of scholastic
studies of the phrases because that's
not what the meaning is and uh by
putting it there you're pretty much
again comes back to the same avoiding
responsibility uh for your own interpretation of the
uh for your own interpretation of the
meaning that again it's not optional
even if you're approaching just a brand
new text that you've never seen before
you're already approaching it with
preconceived notions preconceived
meanings of the terms that appear
through those phrases and so on
so that's why i said in some other talk
like you don't really
again if you have self transparency
take up responsibility
you don't even need to be
uh
going too far into the study of the
phrases you can even use your own
language and just say
uh consciousness okay pal is vignana
means consciousness okay so now you have
two phrases that you just compared with
each other one phrase is in poly one
phrase is in english what is the meaning
of either of those or what is the
meaning of that phenomena that you're
designating through these phrases now
you will not arrive at that meaning if
you start studying the etymology and the
root of the vignana and how it came to
be in consciousness and so on that might
enrich your information that can help
you look for the meaning but if your
attitude is not to look for the meaning
but onto the authority of the text
the whole domain of where the meaning is
is still invisible to you
so instead of
uh going into more detail more often
than not what you need to do is go back
uh on to the the word that you already
know consciousness in your own language
whatever that is and say okay but when i
say consciousness in my own language
what am i designating what is the
meaning of that phrase what is it in my
experience that i call consciousness
when i say it and then you will realize
that vast majority of your own
day-to-day terms and phrases that you
use are not understood because if they
were you would pretty much be
understanding the basis the framework of
your experience as such
you would you would be developing
clarity in regard to the five aggregates
so not going upon what's in the
scripture means not dismissing the scriptures and
means not dismissing the scriptures and
never reading the suttas means taking up
responsibility for what those scriptures
mean to you as simple as that just
reading a suta right away would result
in you liberating your mind from
dispassion but it doesn't because of all
the preconceived notions about the terms
and phrases that you are reading that
you already carry all those notions
translating one phrase to the other does
not highlight the meaning it can bring
you closer if you know where to look for
it but in itself it's just comparison
between different phrases that's it
in itself scholarly study scholastic
study cannot result in any
cannot result in any
revelation of the meaning because for
that taking up the person responsibility
that precedes your scholastic study
needs to be developed and not abandoned
needs to be the framework of your study
so your study is then guided by the
right attention right attention
correctly attending to things
uh only for the sake of clarifying
meaning not for the sake of satisfying
intellectual craving for the you know
more detailed study of these phrases in
comparison and he uh
its development through history and so
on
that all pretty much becomes a
distraction um so don't go up on something
um so don't go up on something
um that may be true even if there is no
evidence to confirm it
so again in itself thing might be true
but that in itself is not enough to accept
that in itself is not enough to accept
that as a valid premise
so yes this passion might be true
but now i can say yes this passion is
true nibban is true that's it lebanon is
real i've done my work i accepted that
as a truth no nibbana is real only if
you attain it
so there is a possibility of nibana
being real for you that's what would
have meant by element of nibana as
present in everyone's experience but you
can see how that happened in later
schools simply it may be true thus it is real as
simply it may be true thus it is real as
such objective truth so then people
started saying we are already in ibana
that's it i don't need to do anything
because nibana has a possibility
of of something that i can develop well
as such it's true thus i'm already in it
so in other words it needs to be
verified for yourself so as i said if
the phrases are understood correctly
they will result in this passion
so if nibana is understood correctly you
will be in it
so you can't just say yes i believe in
ibana i accept it as a true objective
value of this reality but i'm not in it
well it doesn't apply to you then there
is no ibana for you
so the next one is basically uh don't go
upon that uh an axiom which basically
ahead to means the the first the first
cause the first premise
um in other words don't go upon the
there is no such as the because this
premise is first because somebody said
it first to that extent that must not be
questioned and everything else that come
after it you can question that but not
the first premise and i think probably
the the
easiest example is the like the
generally the christian view of belief
in god so you can question everything
even in like a you know there was like
existential philosophers who were
christians and they would question
everything in the entire experience but
they wouldn't question the premise that
the god is real as such
and that in itself is is a contradiction
so if you question everything you have
to question even your starting premise
that made you question everything so
nothing should be exempted from turning
your reasoning to it and applying these
same principles of creed aversion
delusion freedom from green division
delusion so don't go up on faulty reasoning it's
so don't go up on faulty reasoning it's
kind of self-explanatory this one
it would also fall like a
common sense
or
[Music] using a personal experience
using a personal experience
as a as a argument to apply to these
universal truths that you know the
dharma is supposed to reveal the greater
versus delusion and freedom from it
so for example it would be for somebody
who is not free from sensuality
like actually there was example in the
sutras of that where he met a monk who
said oh the greatest happiness is when
you're free from sensuality now this
person not being free from sensuality himself
not being free from sensuality himself
could not see he could not see the the
that is the truth and then he dismissed
it so he said no i don't see that thus
that's not true
and that's a fallacy in itself like you
might not see it but that doesn't mean
that you wouldn't see it if you make the
right effort
so if you don't see the truth personally
it doesn't mean there is no such truth
and the similarly the buddha gave it's
like the the two friends come to the
bottom of the mountain
one of them decides to climb the top and
when he's at the top he exclaims wow the
views from this top of this mountain is
just like so beautiful you can't even
describe them the man at the bottom of
the mountain says turns around he
doesn't see anything just some forest
and he says no i don't believe that's
the truth because i don't see it for
myself so then the man from the top comes takes
so then the man from the top comes takes
him by the arm drags him up to the top
of the mountain and says do you see now
and then he agreed to yes so it's it's
it's the same if somebody wants to see
the benefit
of freedom from centrality they cannot
see it before they are free from
sensuality um and it's even worse than if they
um and it's even worse than if they
cannot see it before they're free from
centrality and then they choose to
dismiss it as well because they can't
see it
uh then they will never decide to climb
that hill and see the benefit for
themselves don't go up on bias
don't go up on bias
so and that again everybody starts with
the bias so
but don't go upon bias means
don't go upon bias means
start questioning
putting yourself in question that even
when you're absolutely certain you might
be biased
so if you don't know for sure
what the right view is what freedom from
three diversion delusion is means you
are biased whether you see it or not
thus it will be safer for you
it will be safer for you
in terms of the authentic uh
contradiction-free type of reflection
that can result in the right view it
will be safer for you to regard yourself
as already biased even if you don't
think you are
because if you truly are not biased
putting yourself in doubt will not
affect you and that's why sothebana is
beyond doubt um don't go upon another's
apparent competence and that's um that's
if somebody's just um like again a
confident speaker
seems to know everything sim says an
answer have an answer to everything
even if he might be the buddha himself
talking the absolute truths if you
choose to regard things that he's saying
is an objective truth because the manner
of the way he's saying then because of
his competence about it that still does
not absorb you from not seeing those
things for yourself in other words for
yourself in other words
even the ultimate truth that the buddha
teaches unless you have the right view
is not your truth does not apply to you
so the the apparent competence of
another cannot be used as an objective
truth objective value that you were
partaking in unless you saw it for
yourself in which case you wouldn't need
competence of another you wouldn't need
majority you wouldn't need tradition to support
you wouldn't need tradition to support
you you wouldn't need people to agree
with you another another suitable man
said who has developed the right view he says
who has developed the right view he says
even if the whole world says the buddha
is wrong
the dhamma's wrong
he knows that's not true because he saw
dhamma for himself
so in other words he cannot be
swayed by any of these external
standpoints because he sees the court
the root of the problem and he sees the
way out and the root of the problem is
greed aversion delusion that affects
your thinking affects your bias affects
your perception your reasoning
perception your reasoning
makes you avoid responsibility for
pretty much already implying meaning in
phrasing in in in scriptures and
tradition and everything else but at the
same time claiming no it's because of
the traditions because of the scriptures
not because of how i took it to mean
and the point to make here is that
this can sound can sound
like
some sort of you're just
determined or you're like a like a like
a sort of a fundamentalist decided upon
his religion his interpretation that
it's right and the whole world is wrong
but no you sotapanna in this case has
arrived at that such confidence not
through deciding and through following
this these logical fallacies
but upon seeing for himself a way out of
greed aversion delusion that are
universal in every person's minds
so that means that the entire majority
that disagrees with him or disagrees
with the buddha
if they were to free the mind from greek
diversion delusion they will see the
same thing
so in the end they would agree because
they all climbed the top of that
mountain and that's why even the buddha
himself said he didn't invent the dharma
or create the dharma zone he just
rediscovered it he just found it like an
ancient path that has been overgrown by
the jungle so he just uncovered it
so
it goes against
the the preconceived notions include the
version delusion of the entire world
but it also allows the possibility for
the entire world if they were to free
themselves from those preconceived
notion greater version delusion conceit
and so on to see and walk the same path
so and then the last one is uh yeah
don't go simply upon consideration oh
he's our teacher and thus thus we'll
just listen to what he says and i won't
have to think for myself
uh you know and that that is quite
common people tend to get off onto the
off on on the attitude of you know a big
famous established teacher or
confident speaker that arouses energy in
them and wants to make them practice but
again unless you are taking up
responsibility for that
experience of a confident teacher
you will be
pretty much
projecting and putting the objective value of
and putting the objective value of
practice onto that teacher as if it is
you are doing it although none of that
applies to you
so
uh a monk might be your teacher but that
still doesn't mean that he can do the
work for you
um so that's why that's why it's a it's
a it's a it's a logical uh contradiction
and will goes further to simply
encourage columnists to uh
to start using these more universal
criteria for which they are personally
responsible such as green diversion
delusion desire freedom of desire and so
on
to infer what whether what being said
aligns with those universal criteria they would
with those universal criteria they would
result in in general
uh
wholesomeness or unwholesomeness as the
case might be
so somebody might ask yeah but why is
great bad and why is the version but
again that's something you can arrive
for yourself a world can say no
greed is not bad but if you stop and
think about it
clearly rationally not avoiding
responsibility for it you will arrive at
certain universal conclusions that yeah
whenever there is a bad thing done in
the world
adultery cheating killing stealing lying
harm disrespect disregard can any of those
disrespect disregard can any of those
things be done
if there is no
greed lust aversion
passion involved
if a mind is free from greed can it harm
another can he want what somebody else has
can he want what somebody else has
if a mind is not free from greed my own
mind can he experience the pressure of
can he experience the pressure of
desires that basically start controlling
you and your actions and your choices
and you lose perspective impossible so
universally whenever something on wholesome
whenever something on wholesome
unskillful happens to you or to others
or both it has to be either on the basis
of greed aversion or complete careless
distraction and avoidance of
responsibility so that's why they are bad yes sometimes
so that's why they are bad yes sometimes
good things might be done out of greed
or aversion but that is secondary
the root of the problem the framework
because of which the whole mass of
suffering and and fighting and conflict
the killing exists in the world remains
unchanged yes you know it doesn't always result in
yes you know it doesn't always result in
killing or lying or stealing
but potential for it remains and sooner
or later it will so it's better off than
to not have such
basis existing in your own mind
basically diversion delusion
and then whatever you do will be good
then whatever you do will be good
whatever you will be uh do will be will
be selfless whatever you do will be uh
free from your will and friendly
so in other words three division
delusions are completely redundant for
good for doing good but are absolutely
for doing good but are absolutely
necessary when the bad is done
so that's why it's better to to to
abandon it it's better to avoid it it's
better to give it up
so using those criteria then when you
follow when you hear different
philosophies different teachers
different different instructions you ask
yourself okay so does this lead to
freedom from greater version delusion to
what extent
in what manner
or it doesn't even deal with it and then
if you realize that it doesn't even
address those things and it certainly
does not help
mind not free from great diversion
delusion to reach freedom from great
diversion delusion then then it's not
really a relevant teaching because
it's rooted in greater virgin delusion
as simple as that
so
and then with the god saying that says
does the greed appear in my mind in a
man's mind for his benefit or harm
being given to greed being overwhelmed
and uh and and conquered by mentally
overwhelmed by the pressure um
of greed the man takes life steals
commits adultery tells lies prompts
another to do so and so on so that's
what we just said so it's same for greed
aversion and delusion
and delusion
so that's why you shouldn't go by these
external circumstances
sorry external criteria
majority tradition here say authority of
another and so on
because they
they
they mask your responsibility for the
meaning behind those criteria meaning
for which you are responsible
for as long as your responsibility for
the meaning is covered up greed diverse
delusion are invisible
which means you don't really see what's
beneficial for you and what isn't
[Music] so that's why first you don't go by
so that's why first you don't go by
these criteria
on their own but you question reflect
put them in doubt pretty much
then the responsibility
for your choices for your actions and
for the
uh
for the meaning that you get from things
will be felt as yours you will feel the
weight of it oh i could do this or i
could do that either way it's on me
which means the consequences of that
would be cooler than me but see it's
easier if i say i'll just do that
because our tradition does this
see now whatever comes out of it i won't
feel responsible
for it doesn't matter what what that
results in i'll say well i just followed
tradition i just did my duty and you
hear that a lot like among like soldiers
who are in the army it's like they
actually go and kill people saying oh
it's my duty yeah but you chose to take
on that duty
you chose the meaning of that duty for
you thus
all the actions that come out of their
duty are on you
doesn't matter even if the entire
society agrees that it's a good and
wholesome thing to do protect your
country and so on yeah you're engaging
in killing
which cannot be done without greed
without aversion without some sort of
delusion which means you are engaging in
unwholesome states
that will have unwholesome results yet
you're fully oblivious blind cover up
the responsibility for it because you
projected it onto the duty see this duty
is impersonal i just serve my country or
something like that
no you serve your own interpretation of
the meaning of serving the country so
you serve yourself you're always
responsible and that's not a pleasant truth for vast
and that's not a pleasant truth for vast
majority of people because vast majority
of people
live by
placing their responsibility for their
actions for their interpretations for
their meaning onto the external
authority on to the external criteria onto the uh
on to the external criteria onto the uh
onto the external you know views
religion philosophy tradition and so on
and that's why they do remain victims of
their own pre-divergent delusion and
then subject it to everything else that
follows and that's also why for uh for
example for a sort of somebody who has
seen the right view he says nobody can
be my guide i no external circumstance
can be taken as my guide to tell me what
to do because internally i see what
needs to be done universally to be free
from greed aversion delusion
and that's why also
uh no amount of um that kind of
the majority
the the blame the the
the worldly winds that would have talked
about praise blame uh
um
fame disrepute all that none of that
could really
existentially affect or disturb somebody
with the right view
because he doesn't depend anymore on
those external criteria
for avoidance of his own responsibility
thus when that external for example
majority of tradition
if if they're against something uh that
the individual sotopaner might be doing
he won't be affected by it in the same
manner he would be affected by it if he
is bound by that tradition or by
majority for avoidance of his personal
responsibility so that's why praise and
blame will cease to affect you because
you don't exist anymore in that publicly
assumed domain where praise and blame
apply and you existed there before
because you used that assumed domain to
avoid responsibility for your own
actions choices interpretation and
meaning if you are not affected by
praise and blame because you don't
existentially depend on that assumed
domain anymore
you will not have your will towards
people either
people that criticize you disagree with
you that doesn't mean you'll pretend that
that doesn't mean you'll pretend that
you know what they say is right or
something like that no you you have the
objective more objective criteria now
the criteria of the right view
but no amount of criticism no amount of
no amount of criticism no amount of
attack by
majority or hearsay
none of those none of those reasons can
can be taken personally now because
you're not personally involved with that
assumed domain anymore
so that's why if somebody does cultivate
the criteria that the buddha instructed
columnist to do
yeah they will they will go beyond their
will in as much as they go beyond
passion because um
because um
it kind of goes hand in hand it's pretty
obvious so because you you're not out there
so because you you're not out there
publicly assumed
on the level of of tradition or majority
thus when that traditional majority
might disagree or attack you or
criticize you you will not be able to
take it personally because you're not
personally involved
and then which means you won't lose
perspective which means if say majority
starts disagreeing with something that
you know a sotapanna does
he won't act out of fear because he's
not afraid of them but it doesn't mean
he'll dismiss what they're saying either
you have perspective he'll have enough
space to see
well maybe they do have a point not that
they understand the meaning behind it
but that doesn't matter
so then you wouldn't have a problem
changing the ways or not changing the
ways depending of you know if
if greed the version delusion would be
sort of encouraged by changing the ways
and that's uh that's why the sutas you
know they're like many of those
in the winner especially for the monks
they're many like smaller rules
kind of like circumstantially arisen
responses to the environment to people
at the time but you know monks lived in
certain areas where people didn't want
them to i don't know walk across the
fields during this time of year
then they complained that we say don't
walk across the field during that time
of year and so on so the point is none
of those none of those really
none of those rules none of those um
standpoints uh are kind of directly
relevant to its practice but what is
relevant to the practice is uh being
left alone not being harassed by people
so then the buddha would just tell monks
just go along with those things so they
will leave you alone
because otherwise they're just gonna
hassle you and make your life more
difficult which might make your practice
more difficult in return but then on the
other hand you know there was a there's
an instance when a man came to buddha
and said
to accept his daughter as a gift as an
offering to him because you know she was
so beautiful and many other teachers
would have accepted her or kings and so
on so but he wants to give to buddha and
it would have just mocked him
and the whole experience of offering a
daughter and he didn't just and you know and i'm
and he didn't just and you know and i'm
sure majority of people would have
agreed with that man but see going along
with that
cannot possibly result in in non-greed
non-aversion on delusion cannot set the
example for others to practice the
non-greed non-aversion on delusion so it
would have been inappropriate
to do so even it would have no desire to
the woman so it's you don't always go by
majority the criteria remains unchanged
what is beneficial is what is rooted in
non-greed non-aversion non-delusion what
is rooted in freedom from pressure
pressure of desires what is rooted to um
in dispassion disenchantment
giving up of the acquisition simplicity
and solitude that's the criteria that
must not be abandoned
so if sometimes you encounter things in
day-to-day life
that you are unsure about again just
just stack them against this this
criteria and see and then you will also
see if they're relevant or not
you know like for somebody like say a
lay practitioner somebody who is still
in the late setting that tries to
practice the diamond
yeah putting up with other people
will be will be uh inevitable
interactions with them their demands
expectations and then you you might sort
of be doubtful as to you know how far
should i go what should i do
same you recognize how relevant things
that are asked for how relevant things
that are asked from you are
how much would they affect your practice
your solitude your precepts if they
wouldn't really make much difference you
go along with it so they leave you alone
if they would make a significant
difference like you know i don't know
your parents are pressing you to get
married then you just have to draw a
line and then even if your whole country
and all of your relatives and everybody
disagrees with that
because the right thing for men is to
marry and start a family you say no
because the right thing for a man is to
not give in to greed aversion delusion
and and then you take responsibility for it
and then you take responsibility for it
and if for the rest of uh your life they
don't want to talk to you and dismiss
you doesn't matter you know what the
truth is in a sense you're closer to the
right criteria of truth which is
non-greed non-aversion on delusion that
doesn't mean it will feel like
uh light right
or always justified you know undeveloped
mind not free from doubt will be
pressured will be sort of doubtful we'll
be trying to kind of sway you but you
stick with the criterias that you now
know for yourself are beneficial
even if it doesn't always feel like that
and that's the true practice of going
against the grain
um so so yeah columnist is very actually
useful and it can certainly result in in
the right view
if applied rightly if the responsibility
is taken up correctly on the right level
uh you will not fight the world but you
will not be part of it either by sort of
depending on that kind of existential
acceptance and avoidance of
responsibility through various sort of
externally assumed standpoints
and that in itself is that would
constitute what the word was is calling
the mundane right view which then if you
cultivate you will get to see the root
of suffering
and the way out which is pretty much the
whole point